Guide to the Benedict Arnold Letter Volume 1772-1782 MS 796
New-York Historical Society
Benedict Arnold letter volume
1772-1782
New-York Historical Society
Arnold, Benedict, 1741-1801
MS 796
0.1 Linear feet (1 volume)
The volume consists of a deed, and 41 letters (originals and typewritten transcripts) sent by Arnold and others to various recipients between 1772 and 1782.
Access Restrictions
Letters in this volume have been microfilmed and will be presented to researchers in that format.
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by Samuel Verplanck Hoffman, President of the New-York Historical Society, May 4, 1911.
Arrangement
The letters are arranged chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
Benedict Arnold (1741-1801) served as a captain with the Connecticut militia and as colonel helped to capture Fort Ticonderoga, together with Ethan Allen and his troops in 1775. Severely injured in 1777, he was given command of the defense of Philadelphia in 1778. Accusations of abuse of power, overspending, and abrogating military directions led to a reprimand from General George Washington. Frustrated and thwarted, Arnold offered his services to the British and, while in command of West Point, made plans to turn it over to their forces. His plans were discovered based on interception of his letters, at which time Arnold joined the British and evaded capture. He fled to England in 1781 and died in London in 1801.
Related Materials
Other letters of Arnold's are included in the Miscellaneous Manuscripts collection (MM Arnold), the Gates Papers, and the Duane Papers, among others. Researchers are encouraged to consult the card catalog in the Reading Room for complete information.
Scope and Contents
The volume consists of a deed, and 41 letters (originals and typewritten transcripts) sent by Arnold and others to various recipients between 1772 and 1782.
Correspondence.; Transcripts.; Treason -- United States.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; Greene, Nathaniel, 1742-1786; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Pendleton, Edmund, 1721-1803; Pettit, Charles, 1736-1806; Steuben, Friedrich Wilhelm Ludolf Gerhard Augustin, Baron von, 1730-1794; Trumbull, Jonathan, 1740-1809; United States. Continental Army -- Military life; Wheelock, Eleazar, 1711-1779; Woodford, William, 1734-1780; Washington, George, 1732-1799
- Benedict Arnold: Deed of James Pierpoint, Stephen Ball & Timothy Bradley of New Haven Town for a piece of Flatts land in New Haven, 1772 August (Volume 1)
- Benedict Arnold to Capt. Wm. [ ], 1775 April 4 (Volume 1)
- Benedict Arnold and others to Brigadier General Putnam, 1775 May 4 (Volume 1)
- Major Jared Curtis to Reverend Wheelock, 1775 November 19 (Volume 1)
- Edmond Pendleton to William Woodford, 1775 December 24 (Volume 1)
- Davenport Phelps to Reverend Wheelock, 1776 February 24 (Volume 1)
- Benedict Arnold to General Schuyler, 1776 July 24 (Volume 1)
- George Washington to Benedict Arnold, 1778 July 6 (Volume 1)
- Charles Pettit to Major General Greene, 1779 March 29 (Volume 1)
- Charles Pettit to General Greene, 1779 April 13 (Volume 1)
- Silas Deane to General Nathaniel Greene, 1779 May 29 (Volume 1)
- Benedict Arnold to Colonel Pickering, 1780 August 16 (Volume 1)
- Daniel Carthy to Benedict Arnold, 1780 August 22 (Volume 1)
- Colonel C. Biddle to [a general], 1780 October 6 (Volume 1)
- Richard Varick to Colonel Lewis Morris, 1780 October 10 (Volume 1)
- Abraham Lott to General Nathaniel Greene, 1780 October 10 (Volume 1)
- Nathaniel Greene to Colonel Udny Hay, 1780 October 10 (Volume 1)
- General Knox to General Nathaniel Greene, 1780 October 13 (Volume 1)
- Isaac Sears to General Nathaniel Greene, 1780 October 25 (Volume 1)
- W. Heath to General Nathaniel Greene, 1780 December 13 (Volume 1)
- Major Steuben to General Nathaniel Greene, 1780 December 31 (Volume 1)
- Thomas Jefferson to Major General Steuben, 1780 December 31 (Volume 1)
- Benedict Arnold to the officer commanding the party on shore [copy], 1781 January 2 (Volume 1)
- Baron Steuben to Major General Nathaniel Greene, 1781 January 8 (Volume 1)
- Baron Steuben to Major General Nathaniel Greene, 1781 January 11 (Volume 1)
- Thomas Jefferson to Major General Nathaniel Greene, 1781 January 16 (Volume 1)
- Bob Morris to Jonathan Hurdson, 1781 January 16 (Volume 1)
- Mr. Isard to Major General Nathaniel Greene, 1781 January 19 (Volume 1)
- James W. McHenry to Governor Howe, 1781 January 22 (Volume 1)
- Benedict Arnold to Brigadier General Lawson, 1781 February 12 (Volume 1)
- Baron Steuben to Major General Greene, 1781 March 3 (Volume 1)
- Baron Steuben to Benedict Arnold, 1781 March 4 (Volume 1)
- Governor Thomas S. Lee to Thomas Jefferson, 1781 March 7 (Volume 1)
- Marquis Lafayette to General Nathaniel Greene, 1781 March 8 (Volume 1)
- Governor Nash to Major General Nathaniel Greene, 1781 April 3 (Volume 1)
- Andrew Ward to Jonathan Trumbull, 1781 September 8 (Volume 1)
- James M. Varnum to Major General Nathaniel Greene, 1781 September 17 (Volume 1)
- W. Heath to Major General Schuyler, 1781 September 17 (Volume 1)
- William Davies to General Nathaniel Greene, 1782 March 14 (Volume 1)
- Benedict Arnold to [John] Laurence, 1782 [December] (Volume 1)
- Arrangement of Baron Steuben's troops, Undated (Volume 1)